Daniel Marks

in linkedin.com/in/dmarks84/

github.com/dmarks84

Portland, Oregon 97034 🔒 (503) 686-4002 📞

dmarks84@gmail.com



Professional Summary & Mission

I am a relentlessly dedicated technical professional and engineer with 16 years of experience managing projects, developing and implementing processes, and generating insights from data. I sweat details and charge my batteries working on impactful problems with awesome teams, striving to be an invaluable, egoless, and respected contributor.

Core Competencies

Data Management, Analytics, & Science

Project Management

Algorithmic Problem Solving & Coding

Technical Communication

Technical Skills

Python, SQL, MATLAB Languages

GitHub, Jupyter Notebook, VS Code Studio, Anaconda, Trello, Jira, Microsoft Office, Docker Platforms Data Tools Power BI, Excel, SQLite, MySQL, PostgreSQL, NoSQL (Cassandra, MongoDB), Airflow, Kafka, Spark Pandas, Numpy, SciPy, Statsmodels, Seaborn, Matplotlib, GeoPandas, Requests, BeautifulSoup Data Frameworks

ML Frameworks Scikit-Learn, TensorFlow, Keras, NLTK, nx

Data Techniques Statistical analysis, hypothesis testing, data modeling, ETL, EDA, data visualization

ML Techniques Supervised (regression, classification); Unsupervised (clustering, PCA); Reinforcement learning

and neural networks; feature engineering, hyperparameter tuning, cross-validation

Professional Experience

Data Science & Business Intelligence Consultant | February 2024 - Present

Currently working with education startup to update ETL procedures and utilize data for more targeted, efficient campaigns.

- Coded custom web-scraping Python scripts and ETL pipelines, writing into SQL database; integrated data pipeline artifacts with existing HubSpot database to feed into machine learning models for predictive analysis.
- Built binary classifier models and bespoke scoring metric; trained classifier models on historical client data (13k+ instances, 40+ features [3 engineered]) to identify future targets, achieving immediate increased positive response rate.
- Analyzed and communicated feature importance to further inform stakeholders as to most impactful client features; created custom visualizations of bespoke scoring system in PCA-reduced feature space to emphasize findings.

Technical Director & Data Scientist – Stego Industries, LLC (San Clemente, CA; 50% Remote) | August 2013 – March 2023 Headed Technical Sub-Division responsible for data and product (construction films and concrete accessories) quality.

- Developed scalable framework and database for product development and QA/QC test data collection and transformation; scripted procedures to check for accuracy/integrity against historical test data and to load verified/transformed data into database.
- Coded statistical analysis (hypothesis testing) templates and data visualizations in Power BI and PowerPoint; analyzed product performance for all brands; created custom views for stakeholders to eliminate ad hoc test data queries.
- Built out Product Development (PD) processes and protocols; implemented tracking systems via Microsoft Office, SharePoint, and Trello for company-wide use; lead efforts to make PD repeatable, scalable, and transparent.
- Co-led our Vendor Relations Team as primary technical contact; lead multiple new product development efforts; helped conceptualize, research, design, and prototype all new products since 2016; developed novel, targeted testing protocols, and coordinated third-party testing. Managed Sub-Division, overseeing team of four.

Education & Certification

<u>Cornell University – B.S. Mechanical Engineering (Focus: Systems Engineering)</u> Varsity Soccer (Team Captain 2006); Cornell Tradition Fellowship (2003-2007)

Data Analysis, Data Science, Data Engineering, & Machine Learning Curriculum | April 2023 - February 2024

- Professional Certifications & Specializations (links to all achievements and full curriculum):
 - o IBM Data Science; IBM Data Engineering; DeepLearning. Al Machine Learning; UofMichigan Applied Data Science
 - Example Independent Projects (all repositories are on GitHub here):
 - European Soccer Player Statistical Analysis Notebook; Movie Database Creation & Advanced SQL Querying